Three bounces into this cup.
Three bounces.
- He can do it.
- Won't happen.
You... kiss good-bye to your cash.
- "Nice."
- Never any doubt.
It's a little skill I picked up working
the night shift at San Diego. Thank you.
- You wanna go again?
- Nope.
Do I hear chicken?
- Van Pelt. Line two... O'Laughlin.
- Thanks.
- Go ahead.
- What?
You always say something
when O'Loughlin calls.
There's nothing to say.
I'm over it.
Who are you and what have
you done with Wayne Rigsby?
Hey. Anybody see Jane?
- "Where are you?"
- I'm boosting team morale.
People are bored.
That needs to be addressed.
People are bored because nobody's
been killed that needs our help.
It's a good thing when homicide
detectives are bored.
So why are you calling me
to find out where I am?
"Because I get nervous
when I don't know where you are."
What do you mean,
"Boosting morale"?
I'm buying fresh fruit...
Clears away the cobwebs,
chases away the blues.
- Good. Get me a red delicious.
- Okay.
"Norberto, where are
the red delicious apples?"
- Let's go. We're going. Come on!
- Okay. Okay.
Golden delicious is fine
if they don't have...
Lisbon!
I'm in trouble here.
Lisbon.
How long ago did you get the call?
- 35 minutes.
- Witnesses?
9-1-1 had some callers.
C.H.P.'s rounding 'em up for us now.
- Jane?
- No sign.
Half a dozen 9-millimeter casings...
3 went into the victim.
Got 2 380 casings here.
Looks like one hit.
The guy runs a fruit stand.
What's he doing with a 380?
He's probably been held up
more than once.
Not this time.
Cash register's full.
There's a blood trail starting here
heading out into that direction.
Looks like whoever the grocer
shot went over to the barn
after he took the bullet,
kicked in the door.
Jane was there.
So they were after him.
Boss, C.H.P. rounded up
the 9-1-1 callers.
This is Harold Keel.
He made the first call.
Did you see the shooting, Mr. Keel?
No, just saw two guys in a lot.
One of 'em had a gun.
He was trying to shove the other guy
into the trunk of his car.
Can you describe him?
The guy with the gun had a sweatshirt
with the hood up.
And the other guy was smaller,
in a suit...
No not really a suit,
but like a vest.
- Your name?
- I'm Sherry Winger. I heard the shots.
- But you didn't see anything?
- I just heard them while driving by
but about a minute later
a car booked past me
going about 100.
Took the exit ramp on
the highway going north.
- What did the car look like?
- Sedan, brownish-yellow.
- You get a look at the license plates?
- I think it was blue and purple.
- That's an Arizona plate. I'm on it.
- Sergeant?
Yeah?
We need a roadblock set up 100 miles north
looking for that car
also an aircraft checking out
the side roads.
Have one of your men
stay with both the witnesses
and run their licenses.
Make sure they're clean.
You got it.
- We need the FBI on this.
- I'll make the call.
If Jane were here, he...
he'd make some snarky remark
about something we missed
at the crime scene.
So?
What is it?
Hands out.
Looks pretty painful.
- Shut up.
- I could help make that hurt less.
Right.
Hey, what is this about?
Why... Why am I here?
Hey...
C.H.P.'s got nothing
on the roadblocks yet.
Keep checking. Don't wait
for them to report in.
The phone company's sending
over Jane's records.
Run his calls. We need to know
who he was talking to...
and what he was talking about.
It feels weird to go through Jane's phone.
He'd hate it.
He'll hate it a lot more
if we don't find him.
Teresa.
- I can't talk press right now, Brenda.
- It's about Jane.
- What?
- I'm hearing from reporters.
The highway shutdown's
getting attention.
There are rumors that a CBI
- employee has been killed.
- For God sakes.
Just give me something I can
give 'em to shut 'em up.
We don't know anything yet, Brenda.
Don't say anything.
That just makes it worse.
It's an ongoing investigation.
No comment.
Hey, Lisbon. You remember
agent O'laughlin.
You're the liaison on this?
Any assistance the FBI can offer,
you let me know.
- You think this was Red John?
- I don't see any signs of it.
Red John is clean and efficient.
This was sloppy.
All right, it could be deliberate
keep you off his trail.
Red John already took Jane once
and let him go.
- Why would he take him again?
- He's a psycho.
Who knows why he does
what he does?
Yeah, well, he takes him
a second time
I don't think he's coming back
so let's just assume it's not Red John
until we hear something otherwise.
Rigsby, where are we
with the license plate?
Got a list of cars
with Arizona plates
that have been stopped
and ticketed in the state.
- Getting the names now.
- Cho, ballistics?
Dead end. No matches from the shell
casings we found at the scene.
- Help Rigsby run the Arizona names.
- Already am.
Teresa, I need a statement.
You already have my
statement, Brenda.
What's this about?
If we don't say
something about Jane
there's gonna be rumors and lies
out there until we do.
That's fine with me.
- Not with me.
- Does Jane have money?
Just enough to use.
He doesn't really care about money.
Okay, so this probably isn't
a kidnapping for ransom
which means whoever
did this is motivated
by something personal...
anger, revenge.
- Yeah.
- So it would probably be a good idea
to get Jane's name and
picture out in the media.
Right. Humanize him.
Let them know we're
looking for him.
We shouldn't make a statement
until we know something.
I'm sorry, but that
is not your call.
Okay, Brenda.
CBI consultant Patrick
Jane has been taken
by person or persons unknown.
We're investigating
and conducting a search...
an extensive search...
in the area. Okay?
That'll work.
Hey. Are you working this?
Yeah. Sorry, I didn't
get a chance to call.
- It's okay. I'll find you later.
- Right.
We didn't need to share this
with the public.
Yes, we did.
And, Teresa, not saying
something doesn't mean
that something isn't happening.
I know.
So, can you get me a
rundown on his enemies?
You mean, the bad guys?
Or the cops, lawyers...
What, he messed with
cops that badly?
Oh, yes but I don't think a cop
would come after a citizen over Jane.
All right. So what about
his personal life...
- Family, friends, lovers?
- He's a loner.
We're his family, pretty much.
I went through Jane's calls
for the past three weeks.
They're all case-related.
Nothing else.
- Look further back.
- Okay.
Didn't one of Jane's old
psychic clients come after him?
Yeah, we're going
through his client list
but why come after him now?
I mean, it's been so long
since he was in that game.
Right. Which leads us
to the inevitable conclusion.
I think someone Jane put away
is getting back at him.
Maybe they've been released.
Maybe they're reaching out
from prison.
Whichever it is,
we need to go through
every case Jane's worked on
since he came to the CBI.
Van Pelt, start digging.
Whoever did this has probably
been unhappy a long time.
Everything okay?
You said... you can
make it hurt less.
Sure. I can do that.
What'd you mean by that?
Pain's in the mind
and that's my specialty.
You got some kind of pill on you?
No. No.
Just relax. Look at me.
Let my voice take
the place of the pain.
Feel the pain getting smaller.
Feel the pain going away.
It's folding in on itself.
Folding...
And you're feeling relaxed...
and calm.
Hello, Patrick.
Do you remember me?
Maybe.
That means you don't.
No, it just means that I
have difficulty talking
when someone is
pointing a gun at me.
Why?
- Does it make you scared?
- Yes, it does.
I don't like being bullied.
Please put the gun down.
I like the look on your face
right now too much.
Then just take a photograph.
Please put the gun down. I...
If you are gonna kill me, then you
would've killed me already.
Whatever you want from me,
you're not gonna get it
unless you put the gun down.
Thank you.
You don't remember me, do you?
Is that strange?
Given the way you're carrying
yourself, I'd be surprised
if your own mother recognized you.
Well, my mother died when I was born
so you're probably right.
Sorry. Bad choice.
Little harsh on your
colleague there.
Who cares about him?
I can't believe this.
You're here.
I mean, you're really...
you're really here.
Yeah. I'm... I'm here.
So what's the plan, Rachel?
So you do know who I am.
How many motherless 23-year-olds
with a slight pigeon-toed stance
and a hint of a new
England childhood
in their voice do
you think I've met?
It was a trick then...
the comment about my mother.
You are a sly one, Mr. Jane.
- This is about your father, isn't it?
- We're not going to talk about this.
We can talk about whatever
you wanna talk about.
- No. We're not gonna talk, period.
- Okay.
I know what you do
when you talk to people...
That gentle hand on their
shoulder, the long look in their eyes.
You're not doing that to me.
I don't know what
you're talking about.
- You think I'm stupid.
- No, I don't.
You think everybody's
stupid except for you.
- You're wrong.
- No. No.
You don't even know
what's going on here.
I am going to kill you.
But I am going to hurt you first.
I have to take my medication now.
"And everyone at CBI
is hoping and working"
"for the safe return of our friend
and colleague."
"We also want to extend our condolences
to the family of Norberto Rivera"
"who died trying to help Mr. Jane."
"The CBI is offering a $10,000
reward for anyone"
"providing information
leading to the return of Mr. Jane."
"We are going to put up
a phone number."
"We encourage anyone
with relevant information to call."
"Thank you."
These are Jane's cases.
We need a disposition on each case.
Is the suspect in jail?
If not, where are they?
- Then look for anything that sticks out.
- Okay.
- More cases?
- Complaints.
I went down to the outreach
officer in Community Relations
and asked if they
had a file on Jane.
- Looks like there's more than one.
- He has his own filing cabinet.
Have Bob in Admin have his juniors
help you do a preliminary search.
I'll clear it with Hightower.
I got something.
C.H.P. got a call from a rancher
outside Wilton.
Says one of his workers
saw a car on a private road
that runs through his land
a few hours ago.
A farmhand approached the car.
Driver waved a gun at him.
Wilton? That's south
of where Jane was taken.
The witness said
he was going north.
I'll get Wilton P.D.
to check it out.
You go. O'Laughlin,
you mind going with him?
We've already had one
person taken today.
Until we know what's going on
I don't want anyone
going anywhere alone.
- Sure.
- Let's go.
- Thanks for coming along.
- No problem.
- Second set of eyes. Always good.
- Yeah.
I'll drive.
Aren't you working
Jane's case files?
Lisbon wants me to go
through his desk first.
Not that any of this
is getting use anywhere.
- You ever seen where he keeps the key?
- No.
I'll get tech services
to have 'em pop the lock.
Nah, that'll take too long. Here.
Thanks.
Don't tell Jane I did that.
Okay.
Cough drops.
Superglue.
Clippings.
Big help.
Well, it figures Jane's not gonna
keep anything important in the office.
Wait. There's something
else in here.
What do you mean?
It's taped to the
top of the drawer.
You think he's dead?
Cho.
Who?
Hey, boss. Call for you.
Linus Wagner from county jail.
- Line two.
- Linus Wagner?
He says it's about Jane.
Who's Linus Wagner?
He's this creepy doctor that Jane put away
a couple years ago.
He... he killed two people
and tried to make it look like
Red John did it.
This is Lisbon.
Agent. Dr. Linus Wagner.
How are you?
What's this about?
"I happened to see on the TV
in our recreation area"
the announcement
about Patrick Jane.
Very sorry to hear it.
I hope he's all right.
Yeah, I'm sure. Do you
have information about him?
"Yes. Yes, I think I may."
Why don't you come out here,
and we can talk about it?
Just tell me.
No. You should come.
It's complicated.
- Mr. Mendoza?
- Yeah?
Wayne Rigsby, CBI.
You called C.H.P. about the car?
- That's right.
- You could've mentioned it was on fire.
Well, it wasn't. Not... not then.
One of my hands saw a car on our road
with a guy holding a gun
so I called the cops.
A little later I saw smoke,
so I called the Fire Department.
You could've given us a heads-up.
Why? You guys put out fires?
Your guy get a look at the driver?
Can he give us a description?
No. Uh, he said he was
wearing a sweatshirt
with, uh, with the hood up.
Thanks.
I have nothing. You?
Nope.
We got California plates.
Second thing the witness
got wrong. Typical.
Look, they must've brought Jane
here and switched to another car.
Yep. It's stolen.
Forensics can sift the ashes.
We should get back to the office.
Rigsby?
What people don't realize
is when they torch a car
the gas tank goes first.
Whole thing burns back to front.
So the trunk gets incinerated,
but sometimes...
Sometimes stuff up front survives.
Well, the car's stolen.
Paperwork's useless.
The guy who took Jane...
he got shot, right?
So he's driving, and he's bleeding.
He's looking for something
to put on the wound.
What do people do when they're driving
and they're looking for something
in the glove compartment?
This...
We take to forensics.
A fingerprint.
No need. Hold it up.
Why?
Bureau techs can scan
the image into A.F.I.S.
If he's in the system,
we'll have an I.D. In ten minutes.
Nice catch.
Yeah.
Thanks.
The print Rigsby found
matches a guy named Fred Kittel
a thug out of Yuba City.
Arrests for assault, armed robbery,
and attempted murder.
- Where's the Jane connection?
- I can't see one.
He wasn't involved
in any of Jane's cases
and he's never been
questioned by the CBI.
So very likely he's a hired hand.
Somebody checking his residence?
Yuba City P.D. went.
Say it's empty, stripped.
- They're circulating his picture.
- Okay.
Check his family, running buddies,
cellmates, employers.
There's gotta be a connection.
Thank you.
Thank you for making
the trip, agent.
Why am I here, Wagner?
- I, I do hope we can be cordial.
- What's the information?
I've been in contact with the person
behind Jane's disappearance.
Who's that?
First things first.
What do you want?
I don't know if you've
kept up with my trial.
It was long
and... tedious.
Unfortunately, it concluded
with my conviction
on two counts of
first-degree murder
so the death penalty is an option.
That sounds about right.
Sentencing is in a few weeks.
The judge might be convinced
to choose something... lesser.
Life in prison, say.
Preferable, from my point of view
but I need people to
testify on my behalf
to ask for clemency
and who better than a CBI agent?
Clemency?
On what possible grounds?
For compassion's sake and... and...
Humanity
more than any particular
personal worth I might have.
Although I did do a great deal
of good in my time, as you know.
There are villages in Africa...
You killed and mutilated
two people.
I'm aware of that.
If you help us with Jane
we can help make your
life easier in here.
Agent, I'm about to
be put on death row.
Do you really think I care about extra
soap and cheeseburgers?
Your friend Jane is very clever
but I don't think he realizes
the rageful feelings his
trickery can provoke.
I've felt that rage.
I've thought of various unpleasant things
I would do to him
and right now someone is acting
on thoughts like those.
Aren't you worried
what's being done to him?
There are things so much
worse than killing a man.
You can go to hell.
And when they kill you,
I'm gonna be there to watch.
Come on.
I will tell them that
you helped on a case
and ask for clemency
but only if your information
brings Jane back alive.
- I don't control that.
- I don't care.
I've done a lot of writing in here.
The bountiful free time.
A while back,
I published an article
in an online journal
about emotional trauma
and its effect on the psyche.
It included some
observations on Jane.
Not long after
I got a letter from a young woman
who claimed to be a graduate
student in psychology.
She said she was researching Jane
but she didn't know a lick
about psychology.
She was, however
obsessed with Jane...
And exceedingly hostile toward him.
What's her name?
You, uh...
You planning on doing
anything about him?
No.
That's not very hygienic.
You know, maybe you can
just shove him in the corner
before he starts to smell.
I mean, I'd do it myself, but...
No.
Fine.
That smell gets in your drapes,
you're never getting it out.
- You think everything's funny.
- Just the funny things.
You never feel guilty, do you?
I feel guilty every
minute of every day.
See? You did it.
You got me talking again,
trying to mess with my mind.
It's abusive, what you do.
You use people...
Like toys.
No thought for the damage you do
the people you hurt.
I'm sorry about your father.
- Maybe you think you are.
- I am.
No, you're not yet.
You will be.
You ever see a rancher
use a cattle prod?
No. No, Rachel.
Cattle can be stubborn.
Takes a real jolt
to get them going.
It must hurt.
You'll have to let me know.
No.
So Wagner says Sherry Winger
was after Jane...
The girl who was the witness?
I thought C.H.P. checked her out.
Now they're saying the license
and registration are fakes...
Top dollar forgeries.
They never would've caught it if
they hadn't taken a second look.
So do we have any idea
who Sherry Winger really is
or where she is?
No. No. The only thing we know
for sure is that she hated Jane.
Linus gave me copies of
the letters she wrote him.
I gave the originals to forensics
so they could run the paper.
Why would she show up at the scene?
It seems like the last place
she'd wanna be.
Misdirection. She gives us
the wrong license plate...
We head north
instead of going south.
Boss, I've read something
else written by this person.
You sure?
Yeah, there are phrases
that I've seen before.
This one calls Jane a
coyote-like trickster
And in one of these...
Where... here.
In this one.
Calls Jane a trickster, a coyote.
- Who wrote that letter?
- It's from the daughter of Don Bowman.
Get a copy of Sherry
Winger's license.
Who's Don Bowman?
Case from three years ago.
Insurance company executive.
He was writing fake policies
and cashing them in.
Company auditor found out,
so Bowman killed him.
That's Bowman.
- And Jane put him away?
- He had a daughter... Rachel, 19.
He was a single father.
She idolized him. He adored her.
Okay.
Jane forges a letter to Bowman
under Rachel's name.
Claiming she's discovered proof
that he committed the murder.
She's devastated, doesn't know
whether to go to the police or kill herself.
- So Bowman races to his daughter.
- He's so sorry. He did it all for her.
She needs to keep the secret.
And you're there?
Jane has you there?
We got the whole
conversation on tape.
Just checked the records.
Don Bowman and Fred Kittel
were both imprisoned at Corcoran
at the same time.
That's the connection.
- But Bowman couldn't be behind this.
- Why not?
He's dead. Died in prison
about a year ago.
Bowman's dead,
but his daughter isn't.
Is that the driver's license picture?
Look at this.
Let me see that.
Rachel Bowman. Sherry Winger.
Oh, Miss Rachel's had some
work done, but that's her.
- Get her address fast.
- Okay.
You didn't know that my father
died in prison, did you?
No.
Of an infection.
Do you know how
incredibly stupid that is?
Simple antibiotics
could've saved him...
But a prison hospital...
It's... it's a nightmare in there.
They just let him die
but you killed him.
- You know, your anger is misplaced.
- Oh, really?
You can't be angry with your father
so... here I am.
Don't you dare say that.
My father loved me.
He took care of me, provided for me.
I'm all he ever cared about.
Yes, you are, and he wouldn't
want you doing this.
Oh, I think he would be very proud.
He loved me so much
and you made me betray him.
When you were talking to me
asking about me and my dad...
I thought that you were
actually concerned.
I mean, I thought
that you liked me.
You want me to be sorry? Okay.
I am sorry.
I'm sorry that the loss of
your father drove you mad.
But I don't regret
what I did to him.
He was a thief and a murderer.
And I did everything I could
to catch him
because that's just who I am.
- You set?
- Yeah.
Go!
- "Clear!"
- "Kitchen clear!"
"Second story clear!"
House is empty!
There's dust everywhere!
- It looks like she's been gone for weeks!
- Basement?
- Nothin'!
- All right, let's get forensics in here!
Look for anything that'll tell us
where she went!
And get somebody to turn off
that damn alarm!
There's somebody in my house.
I gotta go.
I'll be back.
Rachel, can you please
move that thing?
Please.
Please. Please,
the stench is unbearable.
Over there, anywhere.
Just please, please move him.
Thank you.
Smell that.
Sorry, pal.
So we got a line on
Fred Kittel's dad.
He's got a place just
south of Diamond Springs.
You and O'Laughlin
go and talk to him.
- Sure.
- I'm gonna head back to the office.
I wanna look at something
in Rachel Bowman's file.
All right, I'll hold down
the fort here.
Jane, where are you?
"Not Jane, Agent."
"Just so you know,
I'm looking right at you."
"Everything will be all right
if you do exactly as I say."
"If not, Jane will be dead
in 15 minutes. Clear?"
Clear.
"Drive another 100 yards
and stop at the cafe."
"Take your gun out of its holster.
Place it on the seat."
"Get out of your car
and close the door."
"Walk away."
"15 minutes, Agent."
"Now walk down the street
and come to the gas station."
Let's go see Patrick.
I want two choppers in the air
at a one square mile perimeter
secured around this site.
No car leaves this area
without being searched!
- Not one!
- We have no I.D. on any vehicle.
The suspect is female,
early 20s, blonde, about 5'7".
She has at least one hostage
and possibly two with her.
Give me a second, okay? Hey.
Grace, the office said
something happened to Lisbon.
She's gone. We think Rachel
took her about 20 minutes ago.
- She got Lisbon.
- When?
- Just now.
- Should we come back?
Hey, boss, do you want
Rigsby and O'Laughlin back?
No. Tell them to finish
what they're doing.
Hightower says no.
Wayne...
I know. I know, Grace.
It's... it's gonna be okay.
"All right. Bye."
Mr. Kittel! This is the police!
Come out with your hands up!
Mr. Kittel? CBI!
Hello?!
Mr. Kittel, put the gun down!
- No way I ain't.
- Put it down now.
Hell, no! You got no right
to be here.
We just wanna talk.
Fine! Talk yourselves
on outta here!
Go on!
Get out.
All right.
This is how it's gonna go.
On the count of three
I'm gonna shoot you in the head.
- Rigsby...
- No, it's my deal!
Put the gun down, or on three
I shoot you in the head.
You ready? One...
- Just take it easy, okay?
- Two...
- Three!
- Okay!
Okay.
Why you have to be
such a hard-ass for?
Freddy? I ain't seen
Freddy in six months.
I couldn't tell ya
anything about that son of a bitch.
Do you know what he was doing,
who he was in contact with?
What he was doin'?
Well, the last time I saw him
what he was doing was smokin' weed
and lookin' at porn on my laptop.
You have any idea how we can get in touch
with any of his friends?
No, thank God.
Night crawlers... all of 'em.
There is one good thing, though,
that he did for me recently.
He pissed off my ex... his mother.
How'd he do that?
She don't talk
to him for months.
He shows up, sweet-talks her
into giving him the keys
to the family's hunting cabin.
And then he splits
with all the Xanax.
Oh, I'll tell ya.
I had a laugh.
Where is this cabin exactly,
Mr. Kittel?
Go.
I'm going. I'm going.
Visiting hours. Hey, Lisbon.
Hands.
What's the plan, Rachel?
I get to watch Lisbon die
just like you watched your father die?
- That's right.
- What?!
That's what I thought.
I've been smelling gasoline.
- You burning the place down?
- That's right.
- Rachel, think about this for a minute.
- Oh, I have.
- Oh, she certainly has.
- You're never gonna get away with it.
You'll never know if I do or don't.
Lisbon, I'm sorry.
This is my fault.
I will not let you burn alive
as God is my witness.
Good-bye.
Rachel. Rachel, wait! Rachel!
- You're wasting your energy.
- You have a better idea?
Just so happens I do.
Where'd you get that?
Him.
I was hoping to unlock my handcuffs
but, uh, no luck.
Well, what are you gonna do?
You're not gonna like it.
"Help!"
"Help! Help! Help!"
What did you do?
I said I wouldn't let her burn.
This way she won't suffer.
Son of a bitch!
You think I won't hurt you more?
I can do this all night!
Get the gun! Get it!
Get the gun!
To hell with this.
You all right?
Uh... I think I need a shower.
"Rigsby."
- Hi.
- Hey.
I'm heading out, and, uh,
just wanted to say...
It's a good day.
Yeah.
"I'm gonna kill you on the count of three"
was a little out of the box.
- Well, it worked.
- Yeah, it... it did.
Look...
What I really wanted
to say is, uh...
I hope we're cool.
Yeah, 'cause you... you did
some outstanding work.
Yeah.
Yeah, we are.
Appreciate that.
Okay.
See you around.
- O'Laughlin.
- Yeah.
Don't hurt her.
Or what?
Or you'll have to deal with me.
- You okay?
- Good. Thank you.
You're looking a little creaky.
Yeah.
Well, a cattle prod
will do it to you.
Well, the doctor says
there's no lasting effects.
Well, that doctor should
try it himself sometime.
Well, that was a big smile.
Of course I'm glad you're back
but I'm also glad we finally
solved one without you.
You were kidnapped
and delivered to me.
That counts as solving one?
Hightower and the team found us.
But if I hadn't held off Rachel
they would have found us
dead in a burned out house.
Oh, you held off Rachel.
Where's my apple?
- Your what?
- My apple.
I asked you
to get me an apple.
I come through the valley of death
and all you can think about
- is your stomach... a piece of fruit.
- That's right.
- An apple.
- Yes.
- Well, that's just plain selfish.
- Selfish?
- Yes, it is. Now I...
- Me, selfish?
You're on my couch.
I'm trying to have a cup of tea.
Have you finished?
You call me creaky.
I've been cattle-prodded all week.
I just wanna have a
rest and a cup of tea
- and a little sleep.
- Wish I had a cattle prod.